Cyril O. Houle Papers
Cyril O. Houle Papers
1929-1986
Houle, Cyril Orvin, 1913-
13.25 linear ft. (14 boxes, 1 tube, 4 film cans)
Papers of the American educator, consultant, lecturer, and author in the field of adult education. Collection consists of manuscripts, drafts, reports, interview tapes and transcripts, speeches, correspondence, reviews, films, memorabilia and publications that Houle collected.
149421
Biographical History
Cyril Houle has been a major figure in the history of continuing education as a teacher, writer and researcher. He received his bachelor's and master's degrees from the University of Florida at Gainesville (1934) and his Ph.D. from the University of Chicago (1940). He was the recipient of numerous honorary doctorates and the first recipient of the William Pearson Tolley Medal for Distinguished Leadership in Adult Education (1966).
From 1939 to 1979, Houle served on the faculty of the University of Chicago, from 1944-1952 as the Dean of University College. In 1953 he devoted himself full time to graduate training and research, particularly to the master's and doctoral programs in adult and higher education. He has served as visiting instructor, professor and lecturer at the University of California at Berkeley (1940), the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee (1960), and the University of Washington (1961). He held a Fulbright Scholarship in the United Kingdom (1950-1951), was director of a Unesco workshop in Sweden (1950), served as consultant to the universities of Liberia and Nigeria (1966), andas senior consultant to the Educational Testing Service (1972).He was twice appointed to the National Advisory Council of Extension and Continuing Education by Lyndon B.Johnson.
Houle's research took him abroad to England (1954), to study university extra-mural work in Africa and the Caribbean (1958-1959), to folk schools in Denmark and to Oxford University where he was Visiting Senior Research Specialist in Extra-Mural Studies.(1967-1968).
Houle is a member of many organizations. He served as centennial president of the Chicago Literary Club, for which he also gave several addresses. Houle has been awarded the 1966 Citation from the Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC), the 1967 Award of Merit of the National Association of Public School Adult Education (NAPSAE) and the 1981 Imogene Okes Award for Outstanding Research in Adult Education from the Adult Education Association (AEA, now the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education, AAACE).
Houle has authored and co-authored numerous articles and chapters, as well as the following books:
Adult Education (with Floyd W. Reeves and Thomas Fansler)
The Armed Services and Adult Education (with Elbert W. Burr, Thomas H. Hamilton, and John R. Tale)
Continuing Learning in the Professions
Continuing Your Education
The Design of Education
The Effective Board
The External Degree
The Inquiring Mind
Libraries in Adult and Fundamental Education
Patterns of Learning
Residential Continuing Education
The University, the Citizen and World Affairs (with Charles A. Nelson)
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Cyril O. Houle Papers consists of reports, manuscripts, drafts, interview tapes and transcripts, speeches, correspondence, reviews, research materials, films, memorabilia and publications that Houle considered valuable. The bulk of the collection is dated 1959-1980. The collection is divided into twelve series, five of which (The Inquiring Mind background materials, Manuscripts, Patterns of Learning, Projects, and Publications) are of a substantial size.
Advisory Committee on Education consists of daily reports of Houle's observations, and activities for the committee, arranged by state. Awards contains programs, clippings, and correspondence related to the honorary doctorates Houle received.
The Inquiring Mind background material, self-educating project consists of the research materials which formed the basis for Houle's book. (See below for taped interviews for this book.)
Manuscripts contains manuscript versions of many of Houle's writings; however, for related correspondence, drafts, and background materials see the "Inquiring Mind," "Patterns of Learning" and "Projects" series.
Patterns of Learning comprises material relating to Houle's book which brought together several separately constructed essays, dating over a period of years.
Houle was involved in numerous Projects and with several books others wrote. This large series reflects many of these projects, and includes correspondence and other materials related to his publishers.
Miscellaneous includes correspondence from Paul Sheats, Thurman White and Malcolm Knowles.
Publications are divided into three distinct sections: Cyril O. Houle (COH), International and U.S. publications. The first section includes articles, pamphlets and books in which Houle made a significant contribution. The second and third sections contain adult education-related material published outside the United States (international) as well as domestically.
Dissertations included in the collection either have dedications within them or other notations which indicate their value to Houle. Memorabilia includes plaques, photographs, certificates, honorary doctorates, certificates of recognition, and other similar material. Tapes (small) include interviews of and by Houle, some for The Inquiring Mind and others unidentified. Finally, Films contains four films. Three are Encyclopedia Britannica films on the topic of discussion groups, and the fourth is a profile of a Dr. Corbett.
Bracketed abbreviations in the inventory indicate those used on folders. Bracketed numbers indicated the number of folders similarly labeled. The word "[copy]" indicates that the folder title reads the same as the heading. Explanatory notes about the contents of a series or folders are also bracketed.
Arrangement of the Collection
In most cases, Houle's arrangement of materials and folder headings has been preserved. Notebooks and large folders have been disassembled into more manageable units, but kept ordered as found. Miscellaneous materials are found before the publications; large bound materials and those of unique size and shape have been placed at the end of the shelf list. Specific comments concerning the series follow.
Advisory Committee on Education is arranged by state. Awards is arranged chronologically. The Inquiring Mind background material is arranged by type of material. Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by title. Patterns of Learning essays are arranged in the same order as in the published book. Projects are arranged alphabetically; where projects included a considerable amount of materials, these have been separated into several folders by type (e.g. Correspondence). Publications are divided into three subsets; Houle's own writings are arranged alphabetically by type and within that by title while international publications are arranged alphabetically by country and US publications alphabetically by topic. Tapes and Films are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Houle, Cyril Orvin, 1913-; The Inquiring mind.; Patterns of learning.; Adult education.; Educators, United States.; Awards.; Sound recordings.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Manuscripts (document genre); Memorabilia.; Pamphlets.; Reports.; Reviews (documents); Speeches (documents); Transcripts.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Advisory Committee on Education
  - Daily Field Trip Reports, Summer 1937
    - Alabama - Colorado (Box 1)
    - Idaho - Kansas (Box 1)
    - Kentucky - Minnesota (Box 1)
    - Mississippi - North Carolina (Box 1)
    - Ohio - South Dakota (Box 1)
    - Tennessee - Wyoming (Box 1)
- Awards
  - DePaul University, 1975; program, clippings (Box 1)
  - New York University, April 9, 1975; NYU Report (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt University, 1977; clippings, invitation, telegram (Box 1)
  - American Association for Adult and Continuing Education, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Suffolk University, 1984; program, clipping, correspondence (Box 1)
    See also Memorabilia (Box 10)
  - Empire State College, Oct. 20, 1985; program (Box 1)
  - Northern Illinois University, May 10, 1986; program (Box 1)
- The Inquiring Mind background material [INQ MIND]
  - Interview procedures (Box 1)
  - Transcripts [interviewees are anonymous]
    See also Tapes, Boxes 12-13
    - A-B, undated (Box 1)
    - C-G, May 1959 (Box 1)
    - H-L, June 1959 (Box 1)
    - M-T, July 1959 (Box 1)
    - U, August 1959 (Box 1)
    - V, undated (Box 1)
    - W, March 1960 (Box 1)
  - Basic sheets
    - [Subjects data] (Box 1)
    - Highlights and Implications (Box 1)
    - Rejection (Box 1)
    - Selections from Interviews (Box 1)
    - Tally - How Viewed by Society (Box 1)
    - Tally - Self Concept (Box 1)
    - Tally - Why Self Educating? (Box 1)
  - Notes from Tape Box entitled "Selections" (Box 1)
- Manuscripts [MS.]
  - Continuing Learning in the Professions, c. 1980
    - Print Specifications; Front Matter (Box 1)
    - Chapters 1- 3 (Box 1)
    - Chapters 4 - 5 (Box 1)
    - Chapters 6 - 8 (Box 2)
    - Chapters 9 - 10 (Box 2)
    - Bibliography (Box 2)
    - Index (Box 2)
  - Continuing Your Education (Final), c. 1964
    - Front Matter (Box 2)
    - Chapters 1 - 5 (Box 2)
    - Chapters 6 - 10 (Box 2)
    - References, Index (Box 2)
  - The Design of Education, c. 1972
    - Chapters 1 - 3 (Box 2)
    - Chapters 4 - 5 (Box 2)
    - Chapters 6 - Glossary (Box 2)
    - Bibliographic Essay [1st page missing] (Box 2)
  - The External Degree, c. 1973
    - Front Matter, Chapters 1 - 3 (Box 2)
    - Chapters 4 -6 (Box 2)
    - Epilogue (Box 2)
  - The Inquiring Mind, c. 1961 (Box 2)
  - Patterns of Learning, c. 1984
    - Print Specifications, Front Matter (Box 2)
    - Chapters 1 - 3 (Box 2)
    - Chapters 4 - 6 (Box 2)
    - Chapters 7 - 10 (Box 2)
    - References (Box 2)
- Patterns of Learning [P.L.]
  - "What Do I Know?" - The Founder
    - [copy] (Box 2)
    - Draft (Box 2)
    - Reading Copy (Box 2)
    - Background materials (Box 2)
  - "He" [about Alexander Pope]
    - [copy with introductory notes] (Box 2)
    - Address, May 25, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Draft, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Background materials, notes (Box 2)
  - "The Uncommon School
    - Address - Chicago Literary Club, Jan. 18, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Notes (Box 2)
    - Reading Copy (Box 2)
    - Typist's Copy (Box 2)
    - William Pearson Tolley Award
      - Citation (Box 2)
      - Program, Oct. 12, 1966 (Box 2)
      - Reading Copy (Box 2)
    - Background materials, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Billy Graham
    - Address, Feb. 28, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    - Notes (Box 3)
    - "Renewal" - draft (Box 3)
    - Background materials (Box 3)
  - Foreign Travel
    - "Foreign Travel As Education" (Box 3)
    - Background materials (Box 3)
  - "A Dimmed Radiance"
    - [copy] (Box 3)
    - Draft (Box 3)
    - Background materials (Box 3)
  - "A Firstling of His Heart and Hand"
    - [copy] (Box 3)
    - Draft (Box 3)
    - Background materials, notes (Box 3)
- Projects
  - Carnegie Corporation
    - Correspondence, 1966-1973 (Box 3)
    - Final Report, 1960-1965 (Box 3)
    - Final Report, 1965-1973 (Box 3)
    - Proposal, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Case Study Book - Laurence Hall, 1973; drafts, correspondence, (Box 3)
  - Cook County School of Nursing
    - Report, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Reports, Board of Directors, 1968-1972 (Box 3)
    - Grant, 1973 (Box 3)
  - The Design of Education
    - Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Reviews, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - The External Degree
    - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Notes (Box 3)
    - Reviews, 1973? (Box 3)
  - Fiction About Higher Education (Box 3)
  - Grolier
    - Correspondence, 1961-1973 (Box 3)
    - General Information, Notes, [1963-1965] (Box 3)
  - Harrington book, 1976; correspondence, notes (Box 3)
  - How to Write a Thesis (Box 3)
  - Jossey-Bass, 1971-1979; correspondence, reviews (Box 3)
  - W.K. Kellogg, 1957; conference proposal (Box 3)
  - Knox book, 1976-1977; drafts, correspondence (Box 3)
  - Levi Report on Extension, 1973 (Box 3)
  - McGraw Hill
    - Contract, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1976 (Box 3)
    - Questionnaire (Box 3)
    - Reviews, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - Royalty Statements, 1964-1975 (Box 3)
    - Stylebooks, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - NEH Project, 1973; correspondence (Box 3)
  - NEH Report - "A Proposed Program of Sequential Education in the Humanities in Public Libraries", 1973 (Box 3)
  - NSF Project
    - "The Education of Older Adults" (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - Patterns for Lifelong Learning [Hesburgh, Miller and Wharton]
    - Continuing Education Study, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - Michigan State University Task Force, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Miller's Final Corrections, 1972? (Box 3)
    - Review, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Peterson and Carp Study I, 1973
    - [copy] (Box 4)
    - Appendix I and II (Box 4)
    - Data and Analysis, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Description, background material (Box 4)
    - Draft, 1972 (Box 4)
  - The Public Library's Role in Non-Traditional Study
    - [copy] (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Tulane Report, 1966 (Box 4)
  - University of Missouri Study
    - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, Report, Misc., 1971-1973 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Audio Tape Notes [Tape Box "From Apathy to Action"] (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - James Robinson, 1955-1957; [Includes letters from Paul Sheats and Thurman White. Robinson was a student at the University of Chicago.] (Box 4)
    - Malcolm Knowles, 1967 (Box 4)
    - 1979, [Related to retirement] (Box 4)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1981 (Box 4)
- Publications
  - Cyril O. Houle [PUB./COH]
    - Works authored by Houle (Box 4)
      Adult Discussion: An Essay and A Guide for the Use of Three Films: Room for Discussion, Organizing Discussion Groups, How to Conduct a Discussion, Encyclopaedia Britannica Films, n. 4. See also Films: Encyclopedia Britannica.
      A Firstling of His Heart and Han d
      He [2 copies]
      Residential Continuing Education
      The Uncommon School
    - Articles or chapters authored by Houle, 1963-1987, various; 3 folders (Box 4)
      "Adult Education and Family Life - Part II in Journal of Cooperative Extension, Vol. 1, No. 4, Winter 1963.
      "The Comparative Study of Continuing Professional Education," in Comparative Studies in Adult Education: An Anthology, ed. by Clif Bennett, J. Roby Kidd, and Jindra Kulich, 1975.
      "Continuing Professional Education: Overview" in Education for the Professions: Quis custodiet...?, ed. by Sinclair Goodlad, 1984.
      "The Continuity of Life" in Lifelong Education: Report of the Meeting of Experts held at New Delhi, 1970. [authored with Bettie Houle]
      "Education for the Professions" in Theory Into Practice, Vol. 26, No. 2, Spring 1987.
      "From Craft Toward Profession," in The Continuing Task: Reflections on Purpose in Higher Continuing Education, 1967.
      "Motivation and Participation with Special Reference to Non-Traditional Forms of Study," in Learning Opportunities for Adults, Vol. III: The Non-Participation Issue, 1979.
      "The Third Era of American Higher Education" in The NUEA Spectator, Vol. 37, No. 13, Dec 1974.
    - Conference participation - transcript, 1970 (Box 4)
      Proceedings of a National Conference on SpecialAdult Deqree Proqrams, Tampa, Fla., Jan. 28-30,1970
    - Works with citations to Houle, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Mobius
      [This serial, named after the Mobius strip, is dedicated to continuing education in the health sciences. Houle, at the time a seniorconsultant with the Kellogg Foundation, was a member of its editorial board.]
      - Vol. 1 - Vol. 5, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - Vol. 6 - Vol. 7, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - International [PUB./INT]
    - Africa (Box 5)
    - Argentina (Box 5)
    - Australia (Box 5)
    - Basutoland (Box 5)
    - British Guiana (Box 5)
    - Canada, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Ghana (Box 5)
    - Hong Kong (Box 5)
    - Hungary (Box 5)
    - India, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - International Congress of Unversity Adult Education (Box 5)
    - Israel (Box 5)
    - Japan (Box 5)
    - Mexico (Box 5)
    - Netherlands (Box 5)
    - Nigeria (Box 5)
    - Norway (Box 5)
    - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (Box 5)
    - Sweden (Box 5)
    - UNESCO, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - United Kingdom, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - United Kingdom, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - West Indies (Box 6)
    - The World Association (Box 6)
  - United States [PUB./U.S.]
    - Administration and Finance (Box 6)
    - Adult Education Associations (Box 6)
    - Adult Education Research (Box 6)
      See also Surveys; Research
    - Agricultural Extension, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Black Americans, See Dissertations
    - Community Education, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Cooperative Extension (Box 6)
    - ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education (Box 6)
    - Evaluation (Box 6)
    - General Adult Education, 3 folders (Box 6)
      See also Needs and Interests, Studies of and Students, Characteristics of
    - General Adult Education, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - General Adult Education (prior to 1930) (Box 7)
    - Groups (Box 7)
    - Higher Adult Education (Box 7)
      See also Postsecondary Alternatives; University Adult Education; University Extension
    - Human Resources (Box 7)
    - Industry (Box 7)
      See also Worker's Education
    - Information Needs (Box 7)
    - Libraries, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Mass Media (Box 7)
    - Museums (Box 7)
    - Needs and Interests, Studies of (Box 7)
      See also General Adult Education
    - Non-Traditional Study (Box 7)
      See also Postsecondary Alternatives
    - Participation (Box 7)
    - Part-time Students (Box 7)
    - Philanthropy and Education (Box 7)
    - Policy (Box 7)
    - Pope, Alexander (Box 8)
    - Postsecondary Alternatives, 5 folders (Box 8)
      See also Higher Adult Education; Non-Traditional Study
    - Psychology, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Public Schools (Box 8)
    - Reading (Box 8)
    - Regional Materials, 3 folders (Box 8)
      See also Surveys
    - Research, 3 folders (Box 8)
      See also Adult Education Research; Statistics; Surveys
    - Residential Adult Education (Box 8)
    - Society (Box 8)
      See also Universities and Society
    - Sociological Perspectives (Box 8)
    - Special Schools (Box 8)
    - Statistics (Box 8)
      See also Research
    - Students, Characteristics of (Box 8)
    - Surveys (Box 8)
      See also Adult Education Research; Regional Materials; Research
    - Surveys, 7 folders (Box 9)
    - Training (Box 9)
    - Universities and Society (Box 9)
      See also Society
    - University Adult Education (Box 9)
      See also Higher Adult Education
    - University Extension, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - U.S. Law, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Volunteers (Box 9)
    - Women (Box 9)
    - Worker's Education (Box 9)
      See also Industry
- Dissertations
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9, 10)
- Memorabilia
  - Miscellaneous, Includes plaques, photographs, certificates and honorary doctorates. There are also certificates of recognition, among them two signed by Lyndon B. Johnson. Oversize item is in Tube 1. (Box 10, 11)
    See also Awards
- Tapes
  - Inquiring Mind, Self Education Project
    - Interviews: Subjects A-S (Box 12)
    - Interviews: Subjects T-W (Box 13)
    - Selections: Subjects A-P (Box 13)
  - Advanced Board Course #1-3 (Box 13)
  - Advanced Study Group Boards, Mr. Houle (Box 13)
  - Age and Learning (Box 13)
  - The Autonomous Learner (Box 13)
  - Dusan Savecevic - 1st hour; Lecture (Box 13)
  - Dusan Savecevic - 2d hour, Discussion (Box 13)
  - From Apathy to Action (Box 14)
  - The LAS and ALAS (Box 14)
  - LAS and ALAS #2 (Box 14)
  - Lecture Tape (Box 14)
  - Micro-environment and Macro-environment (Box 14)
  - March 10Seminar - Motivations and orientations (Box 14)
  - Robbins Seminar - 1st session, Aug. 2, 1960 (Box 14)
  - Robbins Seminar, Meeting, University of Chicago, Adult Education, July 25, 1967 (Box 14)
  - The Stages of Life (Box 14)
  - #3 (Box 14)
  - #6 - Speech to Workshop on Federal Policy (Box 14)
  - [untitled] (Box 14)
- Films
  - Encyclopedia Britannica films
    - Room for Discussion (Reel 1)
    - Organizing Discussion Groups (Reel 2)
    - How to Conduct a Discussion (Reel 3)
  - Other
    - Profile C1-6 May 27 Dr. Corbett (Reel 4)